86. Saving animals, one species at a time. In the late 1960s, you could spot one if
you crossed your fingers for luck and traveled deep into a swamp. By 1985, they were turning
up in swimming pools. The American Alligator is one remarkable success story of the American
Endangered Species Act, but there are many more. The Endangered Species Act was passed
to protect animals whose populations were dangerously low. It created a list of animals
that needed to be protected. The act helped stop or regulate hunting of these animals.
It also protected their environments. It has probably saved more than 100 types of animals
so far. The American Alligator is one. The bald eagle, the symbol of the United States,
is another. The numbers of bald eagles dwindled to only 417 nesting pairs in 1963, because
humans were hunting them and taking over places they live. The biggest problem, however, was
a pesticide called DDT, which affected bald eagles' eggs. DDT was banned in 1973, and
bald eagle populations grew steadily after that. Not only are bald eagles a symbol of
America, but they are now also a symbol of environmental stewardship, says Michael Dalton
of the Audubon Society. The Endangered Species Act has saved wolves, fish, insects, and types
of almost every creature that walks, flies, or slithers across North America. The population
of the Virginia Big Eared Bat grew by nearly 10 times in the 20 years since it was listed
as endangered, another great success. Treaties like CITES, Convention on International Trade
and Endangered Species of Wild Fauna and Flora, try to do the same. With proper attention
and enforcement, animals like the pangolin and Formosan black bears can become environmental
success stories, too.